Guide to the First Baptist Church of Seneca Falls records,1827-1883.
First Baptist Church of Seneca Falls records,1827-1883
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
First Baptist Church of Seneca Falls records, 1827-1883.
6006
First Baptist Church of Seneca Falls (Seneca Falls, N.Y.)
2 reels microfilm.
Microfilm.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Articles of faith, church covenant and minutes of regular and special church meetings, dealing with church finances, abolition, temperance, and religious discipline. Also three unrelated items: a sermon entitled "The hard-shell Baptists" (n.d.) satirizing that type of group; "The Baptist church manual" (1853); and "The Sunday School receiving book" (1838-1850) which lists pupils, dates of entry, parents' names, occupations and characters, residences, classes and remarks.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
Records of the First Baptist Society predating the church organization have not been located. Gaps exist in the church records from March to October 1844, thus omitting references to the schism which tore the church apart when the minister began to preach second adventism, and between volume I and volume II (February 24, 1850-July 31, 1853). Issues of central importance to this congregation were church finances, slavery, temperance, and church discipline. Members who enrolled during meetings are listed, but little else is mentioned about the revivals.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Articles of faith, church covenant and minutes of regular and special church meetings, dealing with church finances, abolition, temperance, and religious discipline. Also three unrelated items: a sermon entitled "The hard-shell Baptists" (n.d.) satirizing that type of group; "The Baptist church manual" (1853); and "The Sunday School receiving book" (1838-1850) which lists pupils, dates of entry, parents' names, occupations and characters, residences, classes and remarks.
SUBJECTS
Names:
First Baptist Church of Seneca Falls (Seneca Falls, N.Y.)
Subjects:
Baptists--New York (State)--Seneca Falls.; Baptists--Sermons.; Sunday schools--Records.; Sunday schools--New York (State)--Seneca Falls.; Temperance and religion--New York (State)--Seneca Falls.; Baptists; Church discipline.; Antislavery movements.; Baptists--Education.; Baptist church buildings.; Church records and registers--New York (State)--Seneca Falls.
Places:
Seneca County (N.Y.)--Religious life and customs.; Seneca Falls (N.Y.)--Religious life and customs.
Form and Genre Terms:
Sermons.; Minutes.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Part I
  - Records of the First Baptist Church at Seneca Falls New York, 1828., Item 1
    This volume contains the Articles of Faith, Covenant, minutes of covenant and regular church meetings of the church and of the Baptist Conference which predated it from Sept. 15, 1827 to Feb. 24, 1850, and "A List of names of members of the Baptist Church .. Constituted the 5th June, 1828," containing the name, date of baptism, admission by letter, dismission, exclusion, restoration, date of death, and a list for March 10, 1846 (p. 323) with names of members for visiting.
  - First Baptist Church of Seneca Falls, N.Y. Record no. 2., Item 2
    This volume contains the Articles of Faith, Church Covenant, and minutes of regular and covenant meetings (July 3, 1853 - July 10, 1853) with a list of members with the same information as that listed above in 9 double-faced pages.
    - Volume I page 3
      Articles of Faith
    - Volume I page 7
      Covenant
    - Volume I page 9, Sept. 15, 1827
      church organization
    - Volume I page, Oct. 8, 1828
      council meets to form church
    - Volume I page 15, Oct. 25, 1828
      minutes of the church commence
    - Volume I page, Aug. 30, 1834
      1st letter to the Ontario Baptist Council's annual meeting, which contains year-end reports of temporal affairs and spiritual progress, including membership statistics, additional letters are as follows:
    - Volume I page 65, Sept. 23, 1835
    - Volume I page 73, Sept. 29, 1836
    - Volume I page 80-81, Sept. 23, 1837
    - Volume I page 96, Sept. 27, 1838
    - Volume I page 121, Sept. 1839
    - Volume I page 160, Sept. 21, 1840
    - Volume I page 196, Sept. 1841
    - Volume I page 247, Sept. 1842
    - Volume I page 331, March 10, 1846
    - Volume I page 149, Sept. 1848
    - Volume I page 76, Jan. 28, 1858
      founding of Waterloo Conference Tyre church
    - Volume I page 99, Jan. 8, 1839
      Doctrine of Universal Salvation
    - Volume I page 103-104
    - Volume I page 138, 141, March 5, 1840
      bro. is licensed to preach to the Sailors in Oswego
    - Volume I page 140, 145, April 11, 1840
      Bro. Sheardon visits and quickens many souls
    - Volume I page 176, Feb. 23, 1841
      campellites
    - Volume I page 179-185, Feb. 27, 1841
      Mr. Bachus leads a revival
    - Volume I page 214, Oct. 1841
      problems with the subscription system
    - Volume I page 239-24 2, Aug. 9, 1842
      resolution on the evils of slavery
    - Volume I page 236-237, Aug. 2, 1842
      Baptist Conference in Fayette
    - Volume I page 252, letter for l84l
      discussion of a revival
    - Volume I page 255, Nov. 8, 1842
      unitarianism
    - Volume I page 258, Jan. 17, 1843
      revival
    - Volume I page 292, Nov. 23, 1843
      temperance
    - Volume I page 308, March 23, 1844
      Bro. Pinney, the minister, resigns
    - Volume I page 318
      wife beating
    - Volume I page 375
      "a List of the names of members..."
    - Volume II
    - Volume II
      Covenant of the Church
    - Volume II
      Minutes - begin July 3, 1853
    - Volume II, pages 33-49
      Names of members
- Part II
  - "The Hard Shell Baptists" sermon, n.d., Item 1
    The term, "Hard-Shell Baptists" was used during the 19th century to refer to primitive, fundamentalist, uneducated Baptists. This sermon may not have originated vith the First Baptist Church of Seneca Falls, but has been filed with other Baptist material because of the title.
    This is a comical, satirical sermon, possibly pretend, referring to an uneducated preacher. It also satirizes other religious groups including Methodists, United Brethren, Catholics and Universalists, and their ways of attaining salvation, c. 1860
  - "The Baptist Church Manual", 1853., Item 2
    Published by the American Baptist Publication Society, Philadelphia.
  - "The Sunday School Receiving Book," Nov. 1838-1850., Item 3
    Contains lists of pupils with date of entry, register number, parent's name, parent's occupation and character, residence, class, and remarks. There is one list for 1838-46, one for Oct. 22, 1848-1850. A list of Sunday School officers is also included.